<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/P5/current/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/P5/current/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Natural Hair and Afrofuturism of Black Panther</title>
            <title type="sub">Digital Edition</title>
            <author>
              <persName xml:id="JLU">
                <forename>Jessica</forename>
                <surname>Lu</surname>
              </persName>
              <orgName xml:id="AADHum">African American History, Culture, and Digital Humanities (<abbr>AADHum</abbr>) Initiative</orgName>
            </author>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Encoded by</resp>
              <persName xml:id="CRICH">
                <forename>Courtney</forename>
                <surname>Richardson</surname>
              </persName>
          </respStmt>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Original text transcribed by</resp>
              <persName ref="#CRICH">
                <forename>Courtney</forename>
                <surname>Richardson</surname>
              </persName>
            </respStmt>
          <respStmt>
            <resp>Original TEI template provided by</resp>
              <persName xml:id="RAFF">
                <forename>Raffaele</forename>
                <surname>Viglianti</surname>
              </persName>
              <orgName xml:id="MITH">Maryland Institute for Technology in the Humanities (<abbr>MITH</abbr>)</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <funder>
                <orgName xml:id="MELLON">Andrew W. Mellon Foundation</orgName>
                <orgName xml:id="FIRE">First-Year Innovation and Research Experience (<abbr>FIRE</abbr>)</orgName>
            </funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
           <edition n="1">First Edition</edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>
           <measure unit="minutes" quantity="2">2 minutes of original video source material</measure>
         </extent>
         <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>
             <orgName ref="#AADHum">African American History, Culture, and Digital Humanities (<abbr>AADHUM</abbr>) Initiative</orgName>
           </publisher>
           <pubPlace>
             <settlement>College Park</settlement>
             <region>Maryland (<abbr>MD</abbr>)</region>
           </pubPlace>
           <date when="2018-07-09">9 July 2018</date>
           <availability status="free">
               <p>In the public domain.</p>
           </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
             <title type="main">Encoding for Black Lives: Legacies of Resistance and Reinvention in the (Re)Making of Black Freedom Online</title>
             <title type="sub">Natural Hair</title>
             <respStmt>
                 <resp>Edited by</resp>
                 <persName ref="#JLU">
                   <forename>Jessica</forename>
                   <surname>Lu</surname>
                 </persName>
             </respStmt>
             <respStmt>
                 <resp>Texts identified and assembled by</resp>
                 <persName ref="#CRICH">
                   <forename>Courtney</forename>
                   <surname>Richardson</surname>
                 </persName>
                 <persName xml:id="ALAW">
                   <forename>Ariana</forename>
                   <surname>Lawson</surname>
                 </persName>
             </respStmt>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
           <listBibl>
            <bibl>
              <title>'Black Panther' Costume Designer Ruth E. Carter On the Film's Looks</title>
              <author>
                <orgName xml:id="NTN">@nowthisnews</orgName>
              </author>
              <publisher>
                <orgName xml:id="TWITTER">Twitter</orgName>
              </publisher>
              <pubPlace ref="https://twitter.com/nowthisnews/status/965308199560667136">Twitter</pubPlace><!-- Twitter has become a place for black individuals to engage in a digital space freely without policing from an outside group -->
              <date when="2018-02-18">February 18, 2018</date>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="JLUDISS">
                <title type="main">Reckoning with Freedom</title>
                <title type="sub">Legacies of Exclusion, Dehumanization, and Black Resistance in the Rhetoric of the Freedmen's Bureau</title>
                <author>
                    <persName ref="#JLU">
                      <forename>Jessica</forename>
                      <surname>Lu</surname>
                    </persName>
                </author>
                <publisher>
                  <orgName xml:id="UMD">University of Maryland</orgName>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>
                  <settlement>College Park</settlement>
                  <region>Maryland (<abbr>MD</abbr>)</region>
                  <country>United States of America (<abbr>USA</abbr>)</country>
                </pubPlace>
                <date when="2018-06-28">28 June 2018</date>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
                <interpGrp resp="#LUDISS" type="freedom-ideas">
                    <desc>Ideational analysis of freedom.</desc>
                    <interp xml:id="STRAND1">Strand 1</interp>
                    <interp xml:id="STRAND2">Strand 2</interp>
                    <interp xml:id="STRAND3">Strand 3</interp>
                    <interp xml:id="STRAND4">Strand 4</interp>
                    <interp xml:id="STRAND5">Strand 5</interp>
                </interpGrp>
            </bibl>
            </listBibl>
            <biblStruct type="article"> <!-- Provided as an example of using the sourceDesc to cite Black scholarship that grounds the encoder's decisions during the markup process. -->
              <analytic>
                <author>
                  <persName xml:id="SHART">
                    <forename>Saidiya</forename>
                    <surname>Hartman</surname>
                  </persName>
                </author>
                <title>Venus in Two Acts</title>
              </analytic>
              <monogr>
                <title level="j">Small Axe</title>
                <imprint>
                  <publisher>Duke University Press</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>
                    <settlement>Durham</settlement>
                    <region>North Carolina (<abbr>NC</abbr>)</region>
                    <country>United States of America (<abbr>USA</abbr>)</country>
                  </pubPlace>
                  <date when="2008-06">June 2008</date>
                </imprint>
                <biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="14">pp. 1-14</biblScope>
              </monogr>
              <note>In this article, Saidiya Hartman theorizes archival violence and its disproportionate impact on the lives of Black women. Hartman argues that archival traces and texts corroborate representations of Black women as always dead or dying, if not in relentless peril. Such violence dehumanizes Black women, not just in the historical record, but also in contemporary life. This theorizing of archival violence contributes to this digital surrogate insofar as every attempt has been made to recognize and amplify the human activities and accomplishments of Black women, with particular attention paid to their life experiences beyond suffering and pain.</note>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
        <editorialDecl>
          <hyphenation eol="none">
            <p>Except where normalization disrupts the formatting of the digital surrogate when rendered online, all end-of-line hyphenation in the original source material has been reformed. The <gi>choice</gi> element has been used to enclose <gi>orig</gi> and <gi>reg</gi> elements giving the original hyphenation and regularized version, respectively.</p>
          </hyphenation>
          <normalization method="markup">
            <p>All obvious spelling and typographical errors in the original source material is corrected. The <gi>choice</gi> element has been used to enclose <gi>sic</gi> and <gi>corr</gi> elements giving the original error and correction, respectively.</p>
          </normalization>
          <normalization method="silent">
            <p>Whenever necessary, spacing between words and following punctuation has been regularized to zero spaces; spacing between words has been regularized to one space.</p>
          </normalization>
          <normalization source="https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2017/05/15/the-case-for-black-english">
            <p>Instances of African American Vernacular English have purposefully NOT been adjusted to comply with American English language practices. African American Vernacular English is wholly valid in its form, features, and creativity, despite the dominance and presumed correctness of American English.</p>
          </normalization>
          <p>To represent changes and/or corrections made by the original source authors BEFORE the encoding process, encoders use <gi>add</gi>, <gi>del</gi>, and <gi>subst</gi>.</p>
          <p>Encoding includes the use of <gi>supplied</gi> to provide clarification and supporting content, including out-links to relevant digital content and citations of Black and Black-centric academic research.</p>
        </editorialDecl>
        <samplingDecl>
          <p>Use as needed to explain when and why only portions or selections of the original source material are sampled.</p>
        </samplingDecl>
        <projectDesc>
          <p>This project seeks to identify, collect, preserve, and analyze FREEDOM discourse, as constituted and argued by Black users online. Directed by Dr. Jessica H. Lu, this project is currently being advanced by several undergraduate students at the University of Maryland, College Park: Sophia Crooks, Kayla Graham, Kaanita Iyer, Ariana Lawson, Alice Liu, and Courtney Richardson.</p>
        </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
          <language ident="AAVE">African American Vernacular English</language> <!-- AAVE is purposefully listed first, to visually reinforce its validity alongside Standard American English and primacy among Black Americans. -->
          <language ident="us-en">Standard American English</language>
        </langUsage>
        <particDesc>
          <listOrg> <!-- Provided to exemplify proper markup form and required elements. -->
            <org>
              <orgName ref="#TWITTER">
                <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2009031956">Twiiter</name>
              </orgName>
              <idno type="LCAF">n2009031956</idno>
              <note>Twitter is a social media platform where Black people have created a digital space for participants to engage with one another. </note>
            </org>
            <org>
              <orgName ref="NTN">
                <name>NowThis News</name>
              </orgName>
              <note>NowThis News is a media company that creates videos for different social media platforms reporting on a wide variety of topics.</note>
            </org>
          </listOrg>
          <listPerson> <!-- Provided to exemplify proper markup form and required elements. -->
            <person>
              <persName xml:id="REC" ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no92026494">
                <forename>Ruth</forename>
                <surname>Carter</surname>
              </persName>
              <idno type="LCAF">no92026494</idno>
              <note>Ruth E. Carter is an Academy Award nominated costume designer known for her work on several films including Black Panther, Malcom X, and Selma.</note>
            </person>
            <person>
              <persName xml:id="CF" ref="link">
                <forename>Camille</forename>
                <surname>Friend</surname>
              </persName>
              <idno type="LCAF"></idno><!-- can't find LCAF for Camille Friend -->
              <note>Camille Friend is an Emmy nominated hairstylist well known for her work in the makeup department on several fims including Black Panther and Dream Girls. </note>
            </person>
            <person>
              <persName xml:id="JDOO" ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n00015862">
                <forename>J.D.</forename>
                <surname>‘Okhai Ojeikere</surname>
              </persName>
              <idno type="LCAF">n00015862</idno>
              <note>J.D. Okhai Ojeikere was a Nigerian photographer known for highlighting the art of Nigerian hairstyles through his photographs.</note>
            </person>
          </listPerson>
          <personGrp>
            <persName xml:id="BLK">Black and African American people</persName>
            <note>The identification and amplification of this person group is necessary for the reading and interpretation of this text, as this text uses "the Negro" to erroneously generalize about all Black and African Americans and/or diminish their status as fully human.</note>
          </personGrp>
        </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
        <listChange>
          <change>Identify and explain a substantive change, made on INSERT DATE HERE.</change>
          <change>Indentify and explain the next substantive change, made on INSERT DATE HERE.</change>
        </listChange>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
        <div type="video">
          <p>This woman designed the costumes for <name type="movie-name">‘Black Panther’</name> to show off African &amp; Black beauty. <persName ref="#REC">Ruth E. Carter</persName> brought afrofuture fashion to the new movie. There was not a relaxer or hot comb on set. <persName ref="#REC">Carter</persName> wanted to showcase natural Black hair, Afrocentric attire, and African inspired jewelry.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="quote">
          <p>“Our aesthetic was always to bring about positive visuals to the African diaspora in this country. And to dispel stereotypes. To be about a forward-thinking community that empowered the Black community, women, and even natural hair.” (Ruth E. Carter Costume Designer, ‘Black Panther’)</p>
        </div>
        <div type="video">
          <p><persName ref="#REC">Carter</persName> found most of her designers on <orgName>Etsy</orgName> and gathered costumes from <placeName>Africa</placeName>, <placeName>India</placeName>, and <placeName>South Korea</placeName>. Head of the Hair Dept. for ‘Black Panther’, <persName ref="#CF">Camille Friend</persName>, wanted the actors’ hair to be authentic as well. She got her inspiration from Black hairstyle books shot by African photographers like <persName ref="#JDOO">J.D. ‘Okhai Ojeikere</persName>. Actors even got a say on the various styles and everyone is lovin’ the look.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="tweet">
          <p><persName>@tinnkky</persName>At the very least, #BlackPanther needs to be recognized for the costumes. I wanted ALL of <name type="character-name">Shuri’s</name> mesh fits dawg</p>
          <p><persName>@afrobella</persName>There are so so many reasons why can’t wait to see #BlackPanther and this is just one of them. NATUAL HAIR!…</p>
          <p><persName>@DanniDollarsign</persName>Brown hair. Brown skin. Thick lips. Wide forehead. Curly hair. Dark skin. All of these things describe me, and everything society told me was ugly. But after 19 years, #BlackPanther showed me heroes that look like me. It was the first time I’ve ever felt pride. Thanks a bunch.</p>
          <p><persName>@ABisi123</persName>#BlackPanther was such a remarkable movie. The characters, amazing cinematography, costumes, music, etc. superseded standards. This is a movie that you have to see twice.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="video">
          <p>Carter wants to leave a lasting impression with her designs</p>
        </div>
        <div type="quote">
          <p>“I want people to have a new vision of the continent of Africa. I want people to understand it’s not just this dark place where everyone dresses the same with bones in their nose, living in a glass hunt. People need to see this is a modern continent. It has a voice and an aesthetic.” (Ruth E. Carter Costume Designer, ‘Black Panther’)</p>
        </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
